Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
دعم المشرف شاهد على kissasia.cam أو kisskh.org
=Rise of Her Lady Physician=
=صعود سيدتها الطبيبة=
=Episode 14=
=الحلقة 14=
=Cure the Plague or Die=
=علاج الطاعون أو الموت=
Wait a minute!
انتظر دقيقة!
I have something to say.
عندي شيء أريد قوله.
Go ahead.
تفضل.
What are your last words?
ما هي كلماتك الأخيرة؟
I concealed the plague
لقد أخفيت الطاعون
because I was worried it might
لأنني كنت قلقة من أنه قد
lead to chaos.
تؤدي إلى الفوضى.
Ridiculous!
سخيف!
How could you disregard
كيف يمكنك تجاهل
the regulations and put
اللوائح ووضعها
the palace at risk?
القصر في خطر؟
Lord Wu,
اللورد وو،
this woman is eloquent
هذه المرأة فصيحة
and good at manipulating.
و جيدة في التلاعب.
She shall be burned immediately!
سيتم حرقها على الفور!
Lord Feng is absolutely right.
اللورد فينج على حق تماما.
She must be punished!
يجب معاقبتها!
Minister Wu,
الوزير وو،
Minister Feng,
الوزير فينغ،
Su Ye's pox marks have formed scabs,
لقد شكلت علامات الجدري لدى سو يي جربًا،
showing signs of recovery.
تظهر علامات التعافي.
Why must she be burned according to the regulations?
لماذا يجب حرقها حسب القوانين؟
As healers,
كمعالجين،
we bear the duty of saving lives.
علينا واجب إنقاذ الأرواح.
In the imperial palace,
في القصر الإمبراطوري،
are the regulations more important than human lives?
هل القوانين أهم من حياة البشر؟
Lord Wu,
اللورد وو،
as a physician,
كطبيب،
can you truly disregard human lives
هل يمكنك حقًا تجاهل حياة البشر؟
and go against your conscience?
وتذهب ضد ضميرك؟
Rong Zelan.
رونغ زيلان.
Stop your sophistry.
اوقف مغالطتك
Who are you to question the palace regulations?
من أنت حتى تشكك في لوائح القصر؟
Since ancient times,
منذ العصور القديمة،
whenever there's a plague,
كلما كان هناك وباء،
the patients should be burned and buried deep immediately
يجب حرق المرضى ودفنهم عميقا على الفور
to prevent its spread.
لمنع انتشاره.
If I let you go
إذا تركتك تذهب
and cause the smallpox to spread,
ويسبب انتشار الجدري،
who could be responsible for such a catastrophe?
من يمكن أن يكون مسؤولا عن مثل هذه الكارثة؟
You're all healers.
أنتم جميعا معالجون.
Do you truly believe it is right to disregard human lives?
هل تعتقد حقا أنه من الصواب تجاهل حياة البشر؟
Smallpox may be dangerous,
قد يكون الجدري خطيرًا،
but with careful treatment,
ولكن مع العلاج الدقيق،
it can also be cured.
ويمكن علاجه أيضًا.
Why not try to treat it?
لماذا لا نحاول علاجه؟
When someone is infected,
عندما يصاب شخص ما،
you burn them without hesitation.
تحرقهم دون تردد.
What if there are hundreds or thousands of them?
ماذا لو كان هناك المئات أو الآلاف منهم؟
Are you going to burn them all?
هل ستحرقهم جميعا؟
You'd rather watch the patients burned to death
كنت تفضل مشاهدة المرضى وهم يحترقون حتى الموت
than try to save them.
من محاولة إنقاذهم.
Are you truly worthy of the title of healer?
هل أنت تستحق حقًا لقب المعالج؟
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
I agree with Attendant Rong.
أنا أتفق مع المرافق رونغ.
As physicians,
كأطباء،
we should strive to save people.
ينبغي علينا أن نسعى لإنقاذ الناس.
A plague is scary,
الطاعون مخيف
but we shouldn't avoid it forever
لكن لا ينبغي لنا أن نتجنبه إلى الأبد
and burn every patient.
وأحرق كل مريض.
If the patient is cured,
إذا تم شفاء المريض،
we will gain valuable experience,
سوف نكتسب خبرة قيمة،
which will benefit
والتي سوف تستفيد
the nation and the people.
الأمة والشعب.
Your Majesty, please
جلالتك من فضلك
give her a chance to treat the illness.
امنحها فرصة لعلاج مرضها.
I'll keep an eye on them
سأبقي عينى عليهم
and make sure they don't leave the room.
وتأكد من عدم مغادرتهم للغرفة.
If the treatment fails,
إذا فشل العلاج،
I will
أنا سوف
burn them immediately
أحرقهم على الفور
to ensure everyone's safety.
لضمان سلامة الجميع.
- That's right. - Yes.
- هذا صحيح. - نعم.
Yes.
نعم.
That makes sense.
وهذا منطقي.
She has a point.
إنها على حق.
Maybe we'll find a way.
ربما نجد طريقة.
Shut up!
اسكت!
The regulations must not be violated!
لا يجوز مخالفة الأنظمة!
Light the fire!
أشعل النار!
Stop!
قف!
Rong Zelan,
رونغ زيلان،
it's only been a few days.
لقد مرت بضعة أيام فقط.
How could you cause trouble again?
كيف يمكنك أن تسبب المشاكل مرة أخرى؟
Do you know
هل تعلم
what crime it is to question the palace regulations?
ما هي الجريمة التي تترتب على التشكيك في أنظمة القصر؟
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
I do.
أفعل.
But what I said
ولكن ما قلته
is also for the sake of the nation and people.
وهذا أيضا من أجل الوطن والشعب.
Your Majesty, you love the people
جلالتك، أنت تحب الشعب
and govern with benevolence.
وحكم بالخير.
How could you bear to see the innocent die?
كيف تستطيع أن تتحمل رؤية الأبرياء يموتون؟
If this goes on,
إذا استمر هذا الأمر،
what will the people say?
ماذا سيقول الناس؟
They'll despise the Imperial Medical Bureau for watching people die
سوف يحتقرون المكتب الطبي الإمبراطوري لمشاهدة الناس يموتون
and sighing that the ruler disregards human lives.
ويتنهد بأن الحاكم لا يبالي بحياة البشر.
Moreover,
علاوة على ذلك،
witnessing the imperial physicians
شهد الأطباء الإمبراطوريين
being burned to death,
حرق حتى الموت،
they'll doubt if there's any safe place in the world!
سيشككون في وجود أي مكان آمن في العالم!
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
she is exaggerating.
إنها تبالغ.
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
If the soldiers on the frontier
إذا كان الجنود على الحدود
and the farmers in the fields
والمزارعين في الحقول
hear that you watched physicians being burned to death,
سمعت أنك شاهدت الأطباء يحترقون حتى الموت،
they wouldn't dare to entrust their lives to the court.
لن يجرؤوا على تسليم حياتهم للمحكمة.
Prescriptions Worth a Thousand in Gold says,
يقول كتاب وصفات طبية تساوي ألفًا من الذهب:
"Human life is above all."
"الحياة البشرية هي فوق كل شيء."
Your Majesty, you govern with benevolence.
يا صاحب الجلالة، أنت تحكم بالخير.
If such a precedent is set,
إذا تم إرساء مثل هذه السابقة،
what will the history books say a hundred years later?
ماذا ستقول كتب التاريخ بعد مائة عام؟
Perhaps, "The emperor, to preserve the peace of the inner palace,
ربما "الإمبراطور، للحفاظ على السلام في القصر الداخلي،
destroyed his reputation for benevolence."
" دمرت سمعته في الإحسان."
How dare you?
كيف تجرؤ؟
Your Majesty, she is threatening you.
جلالتك، إنها تهددك.
Your Majesty, I wouldn't dare!
جلالتك، لا أجرؤ على ذلك!
I'm just concerned
أنا فقط قلق
that if the words spread,
إذا انتشرت الكلمات،
the discussions among the officials
المناقشات بين المسؤولين
and the condemnation of all the scholars
وإدانة جميع العلماء
would surely tarnish your sacred reputation.
من المؤكد أن ذلك سوف يشوه سمعتك المقدسة.
You're quite sharp-tongued.
أنت حاد اللسان تماما.
The rules, though strict,
القواعد، على الرغم من صرامة،
are for the security of the nation.
من أجل أمن الأمة.
How could I risk everyone's safety
كيف يمكنني أن أعرض سلامة الجميع للخطر؟
for the survival of one person?
من أجل بقاء شخص واحد؟
So, does it mean
فهل هذا يعني
you believe that sacrificing one to save the others is only natural?
هل تعتقد أن التضحية بشخص واحد لإنقاذ الآخرين أمر طبيعي؟
The country is like a giant ship.
البلد مثل سفينة عملاقة.
Sailing through stormy waves,
الإبحار عبر الأمواج العاصفة،
it must cast off burdens.
يجب عليه التخلص من الأعباء.
If I were to plunge the people
لو غطست الناس
into danger because of one person,
في خطر بسبب شخص واحد،
that would truly be a betrayal of all the people.
وهذا سيكون خيانة حقيقية للشعب بأكمله.
How could an attendant know
كيف يمكن للموظف أن يعرف؟
the governance balance?
التوازن في الحكم؟
You compare the state to a ship,
تقارن الدولة بالسفينة،
yet fail to see that its foundation lies with the multitude.
ولكنهم يفشلون في رؤية أن أساسها يكمن في الجمهور.
If you abandon the people for the ship,
إذا تركت الناس من أجل السفينة،
you'll lose the trust of the people.
سوف تفقد ثقة الناس.
Even with immense power,
حتى مع القوة الهائلة،
the ship will still go down.
السفينة سوف تغرق على أية حال.
A great physician
طبيب عظيم
safeguards the people's hearts,
يصون قلوب الناس،
and the emperor guards the realm.
والإمبراطور يحرس المملكة.
Shouldn't you cherish human lives even more than a healer does?
ألا ينبغي لك أن تعتز بحياة البشر أكثر مما يفعل المعالج؟
Are you certain
هل انت متأكد؟
you can cure smallpox?
هل يمكن علاج الجدري؟
I am certain!
أنا متأكد!
Your Majesty, don't trust her!
جلالتك لا تثق بها!
Rong Zelan is not an imperial physician.
رونغ زيلان ليس طبيبًا إمبراطوريًا.
Even an imperial physician cannot guarantee success.
حتى الطبيب الإمبراطوري لا يستطيع ضمان النجاح.
She is merely a medical attendant
إنها مجرد مساعدة طبية
and doesn't deserve to heal and save people.
ولا يستحق الشفاء وإنقاذ الناس.
Nor does she have any experience.
وليس لديها أي خبرة.
She's just bragging
إنها تتفاخر فقط
to save herself!
لإنقاذ نفسها!
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
please allow me to take Su Ye into the side room for Isolation Treatment.
من فضلك اسمح لي بأخذ سو يي إلى الغرفة الجانبية للعلاج المنعزل.
If I fail to cure
إذا فشلت في العلاج
the smallpox in ten days,
الجدري في عشرة أيام،
I'm willing to die to atone for the crime
أنا مستعد للموت للتكفير عن الجريمة
without any complaint!
بدون أي شكوى!
If I can cure
إذا كان بإمكاني الشفاء
the smallpox in ten days,
الجدري في عشرة أيام،
there will be an excellent remedy for saving lives,
سيكون هناك علاج ممتاز لإنقاذ الأرواح،
and your reputation for benevolence and generosity
وسمعتك الطيبة والكرم
will spread throughout
سوف ينتشر في كل مكان
the land.
الارض.
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
this is a strategy that saves all!
هذه هي الاستراتيجية التي تنقذ الجميع!
I'm willing to test the medicine.
أنا على استعداد لاختبار الدواء.
If I can make a contribution to the people,
إذا كان بإمكاني تقديم مساهمة للناس،
I would die without regret!
سأموت من دون ندم!
Okay.
تمام.
Then I'll
ثم سأفعل
give you ten days.
أعطيك عشرة أيام.
Thank you, Your Majesty!
شكرا لك جلالتك!
Rong Zelan.
رونغ زيلان.
You're not
أنت لست
an impulsive person.
شخص متهور.
Why did you ask about
لماذا سألت عن
sacrificing one to save the many?
التضحية بواحد لإنقاذ الكثيرين؟
Did something happen?
هل حدث شيء؟
Su Ye got smallpox.
سو يي أصيب بالجدري.
According to the rules,
وفقا للقواعد،
when there's a plague,
عندما يكون هناك وباء،
the patients shall be burned.
سيتم حرق المرضى.
I'm not going to report it.
لن أبلغ عن ذلك.
Will you expose me?
هل ستكشفني؟
Are you sure you can cure her?
هل أنت متأكد من أنك تستطيع علاجها؟
Yes.
نعم.
But I suspect that someone set this up
لكن أظن أن شخصًا ما هو الذي قام بهذا
to get rid of me.
للتخلص مني.
So, you intentionally led me to discover this.
لذا، لقد قادتني عمداً إلى اكتشاف هذا.
Yes.
نعم.
Now that you're aware of this matter,
الآن بعد أن أصبحت على علم بهذا الأمر،
we are on the same boat.
نحن على نفس القارب.
What do you want me to do?
ماذا تريدني أن أفعل؟
I have a plan.
لدي خطة.
Though dangerous, it can certainly turn the tables.
ورغم خطورته، فإنه يمكن بالتأكيد أن يقلب الأمور رأساً على عقب.
Lord Song, when they find out
اللورد سونغ، عندما اكتشفوا
that I get smallpox,
أنني أصاب بالجدري،
please invite His Majesty to the bureau.
يرجى دعوة جلالته إلى المكتب.
It is difficult.
إنه أمر صعب.
That's why I'm asking for your help.
لهذا السبب أطلب مساعدتكم.
I believe you can do it.
أعتقد أنك قادر على فعل ذلك.
In addition,
فضلاً عن ذلك،
I'd also like to ask you for three matters.
وأود أيضًا أن أطلب منك ثلاثة أمور.
First,
أولاً،
help me confirm
ساعدني على التأكيد
if my roommates, Zhou Ning and Sun Yu, have been infected.
إذا كان زملائي في الغرفة، تشو نينغ وسون يو، مصابين بالعدوى.
Second,
ثانية،
I need medicine to treat smallpox.
أحتاج إلى دواء لعلاج الجدري.
Third,
ثالث،
please find a way
من فضلك ابحث عن طريقة
to make sure no one
للتأكد من عدم وجود أحد
comes near the quarantine room.
يقترب من غرفة الحجر الصحي.
Why do I keep falling into your traps?
لماذا أستمر بالوقوع في فخاخك؟
(Imperial Medical Bureau)
(المكتب الطبي الإمبراطوري)
Zelan, drink the medicine.
زيلان، اشرب الدواء.
Come on.
تعال.
Are you alright?
هل انت بخير؟
I'm fine.
أنا بخير.
Su Ye,
سو يي,
we'll definitely get through this.
سوف نتجاوز هذا بالتأكيد.
Yes.
نعم.
Zelan,
كيف،
after hearing what you said to His Majesty,
وبعد أن استمعنا إلى ما قلته لجلالته،
I really admire you.
أنا معجب بك حقا.
I also want to be as brave as you
أريد أيضًا أن أكون شجاعًا مثلك
and fight for what I want.
وأقاتل من أجل ما أريد.
Su Ye,
سو يي,
if I can't get through this,
إذا لم أتمكن من تجاوز هذا،
remember to prepare
تذكر أن تستعد
the medicine according to the prescription I taught you
الدواء حسب الوصفة التي علمتك إياها
and keep drinking it.
واستمر في شربه.
Remember,
يتذكر،
from now on, you must live for yourself
من الآن فصاعدا، يجب أن تعيش لنفسك
and your medical skills.
ومهاراتك الطبية.
And, if possible,
وإذا كان ذلك ممكنا،
you must live for all the women
يجب أن تعيش من أجل جميع النساء
who never
من لم يفعل ذلك قط
had a chance to rise as men do.
لقد أتيحت لي الفرصة للارتقاء كما يفعل الرجال.
Okay.
تمام.
Zelan, I got it.
زيلان، لقد حصلت عليه.
I want to be a bird that flies over the walls.
أريد أن أكون طائرًا يطير فوق الجدران.
No one can trap me in a cage again.
لن يتمكن أحد من حبسي في قفص مرة أخرى.
Come on.
تعال.
Be careful.
احرص.
(It's been ten days.)
(لقد مرت عشرة أيام.)
(Rong Zelan,)
(رونغ زيلان)
(you must be safe and sound.)
(يجب أن تكون آمنًا وسليمًا.)
Lord Feng, what's this about?
سيد فينج، ما هذا؟
Officer Song, why are you here?
الضابط سونغ، لماذا أنت هنا؟
By order of Minister Wu,
بأمر من الوزير وو،
I'm here to provide herbs for Attendant Rong.
أنا هنا لتقديم الأعشاب للخادم رونغ.
But Lord Feng,
ولكن اللورد فينج،
what brings you here?
ما الذي أتى بك إلى هنا؟
The deadline for Rong Zelan
الموعد النهائي لـ رونغ زيلان
to treat smallpox is approaching,
لعلاج الجدري يقترب،
so I'm here to check on the situation.
لذا فأنا هنا للتحقق من الوضع.
If she's still plagued by the sickness,
إذا كانت لا تزال تعاني من المرض،
I will act in accordance with the regulations
سأتصرف وفقا للأنظمة
and finish the two of them on the spot.
والقضاء عليهما على الفور.
Rong Zelan and His Majesty had a deal of ten days.
كان لدى رونغ زيلان وجلالة الملك اتفاق لمدة عشرة أيام.
There's still an hour left.
مازالت هناك ساعة متبقية.
Lord Feng,
اللورد فينج،
aren't you a bit too hasty?
ألا أنت متسرع بعض الشيء؟
The room is in a deadly silence.
الغرفة في صمت مميت.
Perhaps they've
ربما لديهم
already died.
لقد مات بالفعل.
Lord Song, you're still trying to win her an hour.
يا سيد سونغ، مازلت تحاول الفوز بها لمدة ساعة.
Are you really expecting her
هل أنت حقا تنتظرها؟
to come back to life
للعودة إلى الحياة
in an hour?
في ساعة واحدة؟
Whether I believe it or not is not important.
سواء كنت أصدق ذلك أم لا، فهذا ليس مهمًا.
I only know that whoever
أنا أعلم فقط أن من
defy the imperial decree
تحدي المرسوم الإمبراطوري
must die!
يجب أن يموت!